So, Ma was trying to explain something to me
لذا، كانت أمي تحاول أن تشرح شيئًا ما لي
about Grandma and when they grew up,
عن جدتي وعندما كبروا،
but I couldn't pay attention to her
لكنني لم أتمكن من الاهتمام لها
because I was five years old, and I was petrified.
لأنني كنت في الخامسة من عمري، وكنت مذعورًا.
I had just seen The Green Lady.
لقد رأيت لللتو السيدة الخضراء.
Now, about a week earlier, I'd watched that movie "Godzilla,"
الآن، منذ حوالي أسبوع، شاهدت فيلم "غودزيلا"،
the one about that huge lizard-like beast storming a major city,
الذي يدور حول تلك السحلية الضخمة كالوحش وهي تقتحمُ مدينة كبيرة،
and the thought of a green monster coming for me was stuck in my mind.
وكانت فكرة الوحش الأخضر القادم لأجلي عالقة في ذهني.
And yet there I was, at the tip of Lower Manhattan with my mom,
ومع ذلك كنت هناك مع أمي عند طرف أقصى جنوب مانهاتن،
just staring at her:
محدقا بها فقط،
her horns,
قرونها،
her muscles --
عضلاتها...
all of it just frightened me.
أخافتني جميعها.
And I didn't know whether she was a monster or a hero.
ولم أكن أعلم فيما إذا كانت وحشًا أو بطلًا.
So I decided to consult the Google of the day --
لذا قررت الاستعانة بجوجل لهذا اليوم،
"Ma! Ma!"
"أماه! أماه!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My mother explained that The Green Lady is actually the Statue of Liberty
وضحت لي أمي بأن السيدة الخضراء هي في الحقيقة تمثال الحرية
and that she was waving immigrants in.
وأنها كانت تلوح للمهاجرين.
Now, the part of her explanation that really messed with my young head
الآن، يوجدُ جزء من تفسيرها لخبط في الواقع عقلي الصغير
was the fact that, according to Ma,
وكان وفقًا لأمي هو حقيقة،
long before us,
وقبلنا بوقتٍ طويل،
The Green Lady was actually brown,
أن السيدة الخضراء كانت سمراء اللون في الواقع.
brown like me,
سمراء مثلي،
and that she changed colors over the years,
وأنها غيّرت ألوانها عبر السنين،
much like America.
مثل أميركا.
Now, the part that really is intriguing about this
الآن، الجزء المثير للفضول حول هذا
is that when she changed colors,
هو أنه عندما غيرت ألوانها،
she made me think about myself.
جعلتني أفكر بشأني.
It all made sense to me,
كل ذلك منطقي بالنسبة لي،
because as a first-generation American,
لأنني كأمريكي من الجيل الأول،
I was surrounded by immigrants.
كنت محاطًا بالمهاجرين.
In fact, within my immediate social circle of the people who support me,
في الواقع، ضمن الدائرة الاجتماعية المباشرة من الناس الذين يدعمونني،
who enrich my life,
والذين يثرون حياتي،
at least two are foreign-born.
هناك شخصان على الأقل مولودين خارج البلاد.
My life as a US citizen is in many ways shaped by newcomers,
تأثرت حياتي كمواطن أميركي بالقادمين الجدد بطرق شتى،
and chances are,
وتأثرت الفرص،
so is yours.
وكذلك فرصتك.
There are more than 40 million immigrants in the USA.
يوجد أكثر من 40 مليون مهاجر في أمريكا.
According to census data,
ووفقًا لبيانات التعداد السكاني،
a quarter of the nation's children have at least one foreign-born parent.
لدى ربع أطفال البلاد على الأقل أحد الوالدين ممن ولد في الخارج.
I know all these statistics because I study global migration patterns.
أعلمُ بكل هذه الإحصائيات لأنني أدرس أنماط الهجرة العالمية.
I'm a journalist, and for the last few years,
أنا صحفي، وخلال السنوات القليلة الماضية،
I've been documenting the lives of US citizens
كنت أوثق حياة المواطنين الأميركيين
who've lost people to deportation.
ممن فقدوا أناسا بسبب الترحيل.
And the numbers are enormous.
والأرقام هائلة.
From 2008 to 2016,
من عام 2008 الى 2016،
more than three million people were "ordered removed" --
تم اصدار أوامر (ordered removed) بترحيل أكثر من ثلاثة ملايين شخص
that's the technical term for being deported.
هذا هو المصطلح الفني لمن يتم ترحيله.
There is an economic, a political, a psychological and an emotional cost
هناك ثمنٌ اقتصادي وسياسي ونفسي، وعاطفي
to those deportations --
لهذه الترحيلات،
the moments when these circles are broken.
في اللحظات التي يتمُ فيها قطع هذه الدوائر.
I once asked a US soldier,
سألت مرة ضابطة أميركية،
"Why did you volunteer to fight this war?"
"لم تطوعت لخوض هذه الحرب؟"
And she told me,
وقالت لي:
"Because I'm proud to defend my country."
"لأنني فخورة بالدفاع عن بلدي."
But I pressed to know --
لكنني أصررت أن أعرف...
"Really, when you're on base,
"فعليًا، عندما تكونُ في المعسكر،
and you hear bombs exploding in the distance,
و تسمعُ صوت انفجار القنابل من بعيد،
and you see soldiers coming back who are gravely injured,
وترى الجنود العائدين ممن أثخنوا بالجراح،
in that moment, when you know you could be next,
في تلك اللحظة، تعلمُ أنه ربما تكون التالي،
what does 'my country' mean?"
ماذا يعني "موطني" بالنسبة لك"؟
She looked at me.
نظرت إليّ و قالت:
"My country is my wife,
"موطني هو زوجتي،
my family,
وعائلتي،
my friends, my soldiers."
وأصدقائي، وجنودي."
What she was telling me
ما كانت تقوله لي
is that "my country" is a collection of these strong relationships;
هو أن "موطني" هو مجموع هذه العلاقات القوية:
these social circles.
هذه الدوائر الاجتماعية.
When the social circles are weakened,
حينما يتم إضعاف الروابط الاجتماعية،
a country itself is weaker.
تزداد الدولة ضعفًا.
We're missing a crucial aspect in the debate about immigration policy.
نحن نفتقد جانبًا حاسمًا في نقاشنا حول سياسة الهجرة.
Rather than focusing on individuals,
بدلًا من التركيز على الأفراد،
we should focus on the circles around them,
علينا أن نركز على من يحيطون بهم،
because these are the people who are left behind:
لأن هؤلاء هم مَنْ يُتركون خلفهم:
the voters, the taxpayers,
الناخبين ودافعي الضرائب،
the ones who are suffering that loss.
والذين يعانون ذلك الفقدان.
And it's not just the children of the deported
ليس أطفال مَنْ تم ترحيلهم فحسب
who are impacted.
هم من يتأثرون.
You have brothers and sisters who are separated by borders.
لديك إخوة وأخوات تفصلهم الحدود.
You have classmates, teachers, law enforcement officers,
لديك زملاء دراسة ومعلمين، وموظفي تطبيق القانون،
technologists, scientists, doctors,
والتقنيين والعلماء والأطباء،
who are all scrambling to make sense of new realities
ممن يندفعون مسرعين من أجل إدراك واقعهم الجديد
when their social circles are broken.
عندما يتم قطع روابطهم الاجتماعية.
These are the real lives behind all these statistics
هذه هي الحياة الحقيقية وراء كل تلك الإحصائيات
that dominate discussions about immigration policy.
التي تهيمنُ على النقاشات حول سياسة الهجرة.
But we don't often think about them.
لكننا لا نفكر فيهم في معظم الأحيان.
And I'm trying to change that.
وأحاولُ تغيير ذلك.
Here's just one of the real-life stories that I've collected.
إليكم واحدة من قصص الحياة الحقيقية التي جمعتها.
And it still haunts me.
ولا تزالُ تؤرقني.
I met Ramon and his son in 2016,
تعرفت على رامون وابنه في 2016،
the same year both of them were being ordered out of the country.
في نفس السنة التي كان كلاهما يجري الأمرُ بمغادرتهما البلاد.
Ramon was being deported to Latin America,
كان يتم ترحيل رامون إلى أمريكا اللاتينية،
while his son, who was a sergeant in the US military,
بينما ابنه الذي كان رقيبًا في الجيش الاميركي،
was being deployed.
كان يجري إيفاده.
Deported ...
ترحيله...
deployed.
إيفاده.
If you just look at Ramon's case,
إذا نظرت في حالة رامون وحده،
it wouldn't be clear how deeply connected to the country he is.
لن يكون واضحًا مدى عمق ارتباطه ببلده.
But consider his son:
لكن فكّر في ابنه:
a US citizen defending a country that's banished his father.
مواطن أميركي يدافع عن البلد التي نفت أبيه.
The social circle is what's key here.
الرابط الاجتماعي هو ما يهم هنا.
Here's another example that illustrates those critical bonds.
إليك مثالًا آخر يبين تلك الروابط الحاسمة.
A group of citizens in Philadelphia were concerned about their jobs,
كان مجموعة من مواطني فيلادلفيا قلقين بشأن وظائفهم،
because the legal owner of the restaurant where they worked
لأن المالك الشرعي للمطعم الذي يعملون فيه
was an undocumented immigrant,
كان مهاجرًا غير قانوني،
and immigration officials had picked him up.
واعتقله ضباط الهجرة.
They rallied behind him.
واحتشد المواطنون خلفه.
An immigration lawyer argued
وأثبتَ محامي الهجرة
he was too important to the local community
بأنه كان شخصًا مهمًا للمجتمع المحلي
to be deported.
لكي يتم ترحيله.
At the hearing, they even submitted restaurant reviews --
في جلسة الاستماع، حتى أنهم قدّموا تقييمات المطعم،
restaurant reviews!
الآراء بخصوص المطعم!
In the end, a judge exercised what's called "judicial discretion"
في النهاية، مارس القاضي ما يسمى "القضاء التقديري"
and allowed him to stay in the country,
وسمح له بالبقاء في البلاد،
but only because they considered the social circle.
لأنهم فقط أخذوا بعين الاعتبار الرابط الاجتماعي.
There are 23 million noncitizens in the USA,
يوجد 23 مليون مواطن غير أميركي في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
according to verifiable federal data.
وفقًا لبيانات فيدرالية يمكنُ التحقق منها.
And that doesn't include the undocumented,
وذلك لا يتضمن غير الموثقين،
because numbers for that population are at best complex estimates.
لأن تعداد هؤلاء يصعب تقديره بأفضل الحالات.
Let's just work with what we have.
دعنا نتعامل مع ما لدينا.
That's 23 million social circles --
هناك 23 مليون دائرة اجتماعية،
about 100 million individuals
حوالي 100 مليون شخص
whose lives could be impacted by deportation.
ممن قد تتأثر حياتهم بالترحيل.
And the stress of it all is trickling down through the population.
ويتغلغلُ التوتر الناجم عن كل هذا شيئًا فشيئًا بين السكان.
A 2017 poll by UCLA of LA County residents
في استفتاء لسكان مقاطعة لوس أنجلوس قامت به جامعة كاليفورنيا عام 2017
found that 30 percent of citizens in LA County
وجدت أن 30% من مواطني المقاطعة
are stressed about deportation,
قلقون بشأن الترحيل،
not because they themselves could be removed,
ليس لأنه يمكنُ ترحيلهم هم أنفسهم،
but rather, because members of their social circle were at risk.
بل لأن أعضاء من دائرتهم الاجتماعية مهددون بالخطر.
I am not suggesting that no one should ever be deported;
أنا لا أقترح بأنه لا يجب ترحيل أحد أبدا،
don't confuse me with that.
لا تخلطُ بين الأمرين.
But what I am saying is that we need to look at the bigger picture.
لكن ما أقوله هو أننا نحتاج للنظر في الصورة الأكبر
If you are within the sound of my voice,
إذا كنت ضمن حدود سماع صوتي،
I want you to close your eyes for a moment
أريدك أن تغمض عينيك لوهلة
and examine your own social circle.
وتفحصُ مجموعة دائرتك الاجتماعية.
Who are your foreign-born?
من هم المولودون خارج البلاد؟
What would it feel like if the circle were broken?
كيف ستشعر إذا تم اقتحام هذه الدائرة؟
Share your story.
شارك قصتك.
I'm building a global archive of first-person accounts
أقوم ببناء أرشيف عالمي لإفادات بصيغة المتكلم الأول
and linking them with mapping technology,
وربطها بتقنية رسم الخرائط،
so that we can see exactly where these circles break,
لكي يتسنى لنا رؤية مكان اقتحام هذه الدوائر بالتحديد،
because this is not just an American issue.
لأنها ليست قضة أميركية فحسب.
There are a quarter-billion migrants around the world;
يوجد ربع مليار مهاجر في العالم؛
people living, loving and learning in countries where they were not born.
أناس يعيشون، يحبون ويتعلمون في بلاد لم يولدوا فيها.
And in my career, in my life, I've been one of them:
وكنتُ واحدًا منهم في مهنتي وحياتي،
in China, in Africa, in Europe.
في الصين، في أفريقيا، وفي أوروبا.
And each time I become one of these foreigners --
وكل مرة أصبح واحدًا من هؤلاء الغرباء،
one of these strange-looking guys in a new land --
واحدًا من هؤلاء الشباب غريبي المظهر في أرض جديدة،
I can't help but think back to that day
لا أقدر إلا أن أعود بتفكيري لذلك اليوم
when I was in Lower Manhattan with my mom
حينما كنت في أقصى جنوب مانهاتن مع أمي
all those decades ago,
قبل كل تلك العقود،
when I was scared,
عندما كنت خائفًا،
and I had just spotted that green lady.
وعندما رأيت للتو السيدة الخضراء.
And I guess the question that I keep on thinking about
وأظن بأن السؤال الذي يراودني باستمرار
when I see her
عندما أراها
and all the younger replicas of her that are so obviously brown,
وكل النماذج الأصغر المطابقة لها التي هي سمراء اللون بشكل واضح،
and even the paintings that showcase her in the beginning
وحتى اللوحات التي تُعرضُ لها في البداية
as not quite green --
وكأنها ليست خضراء إلى حدٍ كبير،
when I look at all of that,
عندما أنظر إلى ذلك كله،
the question that my research seeks to answer
فالسؤال الذي يسعى بحثي للإجابة عليه
becomes, to me, the same one that confounded me all those years ago:
يصبح، بالنسبة لي، نفس السؤال الذي حيرني طول السنوات الماضية:
Is she a monster
هل هي وحش؟
or a hero?
أو بطل؟
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)